接下来的下一位演说者
our next speaker
是最著名的推动个人计算机革命的企业家
first known as the entrepreneur of the personal computer revolution
时代杂志上刊出的
was named by time magazine
20世纪最有影响力的100个人之一，
as one of the hundred people who most  influence the 20th century else well as
也是2004年、2005和2006年以及2007年
one of the hundred most influential  people of 2004 2005-2006
世界上最有影响力的100人之一。
and again in 2007
这位仁兄本来可以在这里完成学业，
just think what you could have achieved,
如果他在这里再读两年的话。
if you had stayed here another two years.
没错 yeah
他在1973年秋天入读哈佛就已经对计算机科学入迷，
he enrolled at Harvard in the fall of 1973 keenly interested in computer
但却没有一个明确的学习计划，
science but without a definite study  plan
在玩拉德克利夫扑克游戏中悟到了他未来的商机，
in between intense poker games at  Radcliffe he met his future business
他和他的伙伴Steve Ballmer为它们的第一台微软计算机
partner Steve Ballmer and he developed a  version of the programming language
开发出第一个版本的程序语言Basic,并且共同撰写和发表了
basic for the first micro computer and  co-authored and published a paper on
第一篇关于算法语言的论文。
algorithms with computer scientist christos papadimitriou.
这位演讲者是我们学校
our speaker is a  person of many talents.
众多杰出同学中的一位
a close friend in college
通过记录我看到当年他在著名的普特南数学课中打瞌睡，
i'm using the recall seeing him doze off  during the prestigious Putnam math exam
不过尽管如此他仍得了高分。
despite this napping he scored  remarkably well,
在大三时，他停学离开哈佛
in his junior year he took a leave of  absence from Harvard to devote his
1975年开始，同他的朋友Paul Allen全力投入发展微软公司。
energies to Microsoft a company he had  begun in 1975 with his friend paul allen
自2000年以来，他开始把精力放到慈善事业上，
since 2000 he has begun to concentrate on a number of philanthropic endeavors
为各种慈善组织作出非凡的贡献。
making extraordinary donations to  various charitable organizations and
透过梅林达.盖茨基金，为世界上多种科学研究作出贡献。
scientific research programs around the  world, through the Bill and Melinda Gates
在离开母校33年之后，我非常荣幸地
foundation. after a 33-year leave of  absence from his alma matter
介绍您，威廉.盖茨博士！
i am pleased to present to you doctor. William Gates!
（起立鼓掌......）
(Standing Ovation)
谢谢！尊敬的Bok校长，Rubenstine前校长，即将上任的Faust校长，
Thank You president Bak former  president Rubenstein incoming president Faust,
哈佛集团的各位成员，监管理事会的各位理事，
members of the Harvard corporation  and the Board of Overseers members of
各位老师，各位家长，同学们：
the faculty parents and especially the  graduates：
有一句话我等了30年，现在终于可以说了，
I've been waiting more than 30 years to  say this
老爸，我总是跟你说我会回来拿到我的学位的，
dad，I always told you I'd come back and  get my degree.
我要感谢哈佛大学在这个时候给我这个荣誉，
I want to thank Harvard for this honor
明年，我就要换工作了，我终于可以在简历上写
I'll be changing my job next year and it  will be nice to finally have a college
我有一个本科学位了，真不错啊！
degree on my resume.
我为今天在座的各位同学感到高兴，你们拿到学位可比我简单多了。
I applaud the graduates for taking a much more direct route to your degrees
哈佛的校报称我是
from our my part I'm just happy that the  Crimson called me
“哈佛历史上最成功的辍学生”
Harvard's most successful drop out.
我想这大概使我有资格代表我这一类学生发言，
I guess that makes me valedictorian of my own special class
在所有失败者当中，我做的最好，
I did the best of everyone who fail
但我还是要提醒大家，我使得Ballmer也从哈佛商学院
but i also want to be recognized as the guy who got Steve Ballmer to drop out of
退学了。
business school
因此我是一个有恶劣影响力的人，
I'm a bad influence,
这就是为什么我被邀请来在你们的毕业典礼上演讲。
that's why i was invited to speak at your graduation
如果我在你们的入学欢迎仪式上演讲，那么能够坚持到今天在这里的也许会少很多，
if I'd spoken at your orientation you  were of you might be here today
对我来说，在哈佛的求学是一段非凡的经历，
Harvard was a phenomenal experience for  me
校园生活很有趣，我常去旁听我没选修的课，
academic life was fascinating I used to sit in on lots of classes that I haven't
课外生活也很棒，
even signed up for and dorm life was  tripping
我在Radcliffe过着逍遥自在的日子，
I lived up at Radcliffe and career house
每天我的宿舍总有很多人一直待到半夜，讨论各种事情，
there are always a lot of people in my dorm room late at night discussing
因为每个人都知道我从不考虑
things because everyone knew that I didn't worry about
第二天早起，
getting up in the morning.
这使我成了校园里那些不安分学生的头头，我们过从甚密，
that's how I came to be the leader of  the anti social group we clung to each
做出一种拒绝所有正常学生的姿态。
other as a way of validating our rejection of all those social people
Radcliffe是个过日子的好地方，那里的女生比男生多，
Radcliffe was a great place to live  there were more women up there and most
而且大多数男生都是理工科的，
of the guys were mouth science types.
这种状况为我创造了最好的机会，如果你们明白我的意思。
the combination offered me the best odds  if you know what I mean.
可惜的是，我正是在这里学到了人生中悲伤的一课，机会大，并不等于你就会成功。
that's where I learned the sad lesson that improving  your odds doesn't guarantee success